<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>People | Eric Libby academic page</title>
    <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://ericlibby.github.io/people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>People</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://ericlibby.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>People</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eric Libby</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/eric/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/eric/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Eric joined Umeå University at the end of 2017 and splits his time between the Mathematics Department and the interdisciplinary research environment IceLab. He is captivated by the diverse spectrum of life and seeks general principles and fundamental theory that explain its emergence and evolution. He likes cooking, hiking, and connecting with nature.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hanna Isaksson</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/hanna/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/hanna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hanna started her PhD in Fall 2019. She is based at Icelab and the Umeå University Mathematics Department. Her studies focus on understanding the evolution of multicellular life cycles and in particular how their early structure influences adaptation. She enjoys playing the organ and bird-watching among other things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Josephine Solowiej-Wedderburn</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/josephine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/josephine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Josephine got her PhD in mechanobiology at the University of Surrey, UK. Now, she uses metabolic models to explore the impact of environmental conditions on microbial cooperation. She enjoys swing dancing, hiking and drinking endless cups of tea. She is excited for the Swedish winters and all the magic they hold.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lucas Santana Souza</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/lucas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/lucas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lucas is an evolutionary biologist who uses mathematical models and computer simulations to study social evolution across biological scales. He completed his PhD at the University of Tennessee, USA. Now, he focuses on a key event during the evolution of life, endosymbiosis.  He loves coffee and sweets, making him a fan of Swedish Fika.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rebecka Andersson</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/rebecka/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/rebecka/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rebecka joined Umeå University’s Mathematics Department for her PhD in April 2020, based at the interdisciplinary IceLab. Her project will tackle the origins of eukaryotic endosymbiosis using mathematical models that connect physiological cell constraints with ecological population structures. She likes to go swing dancing in her spare time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Umeå University former members</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/former/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/former/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of those who have moved on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;masters-students&#34;&gt;Masters students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alfred Leimar (Technical Physics master’s thesis: “The evolutionary origins of phagocytosis in microbial populations”, 2022)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cordelia Horns (Technical Physics master’s thesis: “Detecting Social Breathing: Quantitative signs of interaction in conversational data”, 2022)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
