<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Postdoc | Eric Libby academic page</title>
    <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/tag/postdoc/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://ericlibby.github.io/tag/postdoc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Postdoc</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://ericlibby.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Postdoc</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/tag/postdoc/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suvam Roy</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/suvam/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/suvam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Suvam completed his Master’s degree in Physics from the University of Calcutta. He then got a PhD in Mathematical Evolutionary Biology with Supratim Sengupta at the Indian Institute of Science Education and Research Kolkata, where he showed a plausible pathway for the emergence of primitive cells on the prebiotic Earth. He is now working on a collaborative postdoc with Peter Lind and Eric Libby.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lucas Santana Souza</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/lucas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/lucas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lucas is an evolutionary biologist who uses mathematical models and computer simulations to study social evolution across biological scales. He completed his PhD at the University of Tennessee, USA. Now, he focuses on a key event during the evolution of life, endosymbiosis.  He loves coffee and sweets, making him a fan of Swedish Fika.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Josephine Solowiej-Wedderburn</title>
      <link>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/josephine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://ericlibby.github.io/people/josephine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Josephine got her PhD in mechanobiology at the University of Surrey, UK. Now, she uses metabolic models to explore the impact of environmental conditions on microbial cooperation. She enjoys swing dancing, hiking and drinking endless cups of tea. She is excited for the Swedish winters and all the magic they hold.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
